<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<individual_metafile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~p-chatterjee/2018-19/modules/dsa/assignment/individual_handin_schema.xsd">

    <group id="H"/>
    <student id="16020551"/>
    
    <!-- My individual component -->
    <component type="Application Refactoring to SPA">
        <description>
            After initial load of the web page the weather and map have little contact with the server. Any need
            of contact is mainly to the database and its to be able to retrieve information and then display it in an
            asynchronously manner to the webpage. Expanding on that point there are two types of markers, one for the points
            of interest of th city and another for the weather at the city at that time. When over the point of interest
            marker it displays a small window of information but once clicked it demonstrates a larger description of the location.
        </description>
        <problems>
            Main diffculty within my individual part was the implementation of AJAX, as it is a more advanced topic within
            the web development spectrum. It required a lot of time, learning and mistakes to be able to accomplish
            what I required. This was complicated even more when having to deal with so many things, such as getting the
            data from database then converting it and then passing it to the AJAX function and finally adding the features
            within the website. Additionally, by making the website a single page application did not make it easier as typically
            you would want to load another page for other tasks/content, causing then think more meticulously on how to implement
            the features.
        </problems>
        <solutions>
            To achieve the specification, basically not having to reload the page again after once loaded, AJAX was my main
            tool and friend as it would perform little calls to the server but it would still give the user the feeling
            that the page doesnt need to be loaded.
            
            As mentioned AJAX was the main way to perfrom my individual part, that being through just vanilla javascript or
            using other libraries, such as jQuery to be able to help me (although I do acknowledge that using jQuery for
            AJAX is kind of an overkill and does have other features that could be more useful, nonetheless it was very
            helpful). AJAX was used to be able to display components from the database and to be able to change the weather
            markers on the map.
            
            To be able to retrieve data from the database php was needed, this data was then formatted into XML as I believed
            it would be easy to manage and update (we did chnage the database a couple of times so this was handy as only
            few lines of code would need to be added or removed). A combination of AJAX, XML and google maps API was then
            used to be able display information within the maps. CSS also was very helpful as it provided styles to avoid
            having to reload the webpage but still giving a good experience.
        </solutions>
        <hours_effort> 25 </hours_effort>
        <!-- This should be an URL to the working component - maybe part of the base page -->
        <base_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/index.php</base_url>
        <technologies>
            <tech>php</tech>
            <tech>javascript</tech>
            <tech>html5</tech>
            <tech>css</tech>
            <tech>xml</tech>
            <tech>other</tech>
        </technologies>
        <source_files>
            <file>
                <name>index.js</name>
                <purpose>has several functions for the functionality of webpage, such as AJAX</purpose>
                <source_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/index.js</source_url>
            </file>
            <file>
                <name>getvars.php</name>
                <purpose>has back end functionality, for instance connecting to database and converting to XML</purpose>
                <source_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/getvars.phps</source_url>
            </file>
        </source_files>
    </component>
    <individual_comment>
        This was a complex individual part but in the end I learnt a lot and even though it might not be perfect it was still enjoyable to
        implement it and work as a team. A just wished didnt have so many deadlines so close together so I could have probably spent more
        time on it but nevertheless it was a fantastic challenging coursework.
    </individual_comment>
</individual_metafile>

