<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<individual_metafile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~p-chatterjee/2018-19/modules/dsa/assignment/individual_handin_schema.xsd">  
    <group id="H"/>
    <student id="17026432"/>
    <!--- my individual component -->
    <component type="Comments Widget">
        <description>The Twitter Widget displays tweets from each of the twin cities by searching the twitter api
        by geo-coordinates. In addition to the twitter feed from each city, the twitter widget performs sentiment
        analysis on each of the points of interest on the map. When each point of interests is clicked on, the latest
        tweet from that location is displayed, and if moused over, will just display the recorded sentiment analysis retrieved from
        the database.
        </description>
        <problems> To achieve the behavior described, a combination of several technologies was required. The core technology
        underpinning the Twitter Widget is retrieving tweets from the twitter api. These tweets have to be transformed from
        the Json object that they are returned as in order to display them in HTML. These tweets then have to be analysed
        to determine there sentiment. Another problem, that I sought to address when creating this widget is one of overall
        performance for the component. Because the widget relies on calls to an external api, without considerations for performance
        the loading times and network usage of the website can be detrimentally affected.
        </problems>
        <solutions>
        I implemented the core functionality of the widget by using php on the web-server to retrieve the tweets as per 
        my search requirements. I leveraged a simple twitter wrapper created by James Malison under MIT license to perform 
        the Twitter Authentication, and return the Json of the tweets. I then used my own php script to format the contents 
        of the returned tweets into HTML. To prevent the latency of the twitter API affecting the loading times of the website
        I called my PHP functionality with an AJAX request from the main page. I styled the tweets in the main widget for each
        of the cities using CSS in the main style sheet.

        To perform the sentiment analysis, I used two datasets created by Finn Årup Nielsen and distributed under an open source 
        license. The dataset contains a list of value matched words, and by using php to compare the contents of each tweet
        with the AFFIN dictionary, I was able to obtain a sentiment value for each of the tweets. The performance of the dataset
        for twitter sentiment analysis is well regarded, and although I haven't compared the results with other techniques, 
        I am confident that the analysis is valid and useful. 

        I used MYSQL to cache the values returned from the sentiment analysis to the database, both to provide data persistence 
        for each of the points of interest, and to improve the speed the results are displayed on mouse-over of each of the 
        map icons.
        </solutions>
        <hours_effort>30</hours_effort>

        <!-- This should be an URL to the working component - maybe part of the base page -->
        <base_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/index.php</base_url>
        <technologies>
            <tech>php</tech>
            <tech>sql</tech>
            <tech>javascript</tech>
            <tech>html5</tech>
            <tech>css</tech>
        </technologies>
        <source_files>
            
            <file>
                <name>ExeterTwitter.php</name>
                <purpose>fetch twitter feed for Exeter</purpose>
                <source_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/twitter/ExeterTwitter.phps</source_url>
            </file>
            <file>
                <name>RennesTwitter.php</name>
                <purpose>fetch twitter feed for Rennes</purpose>
                <source_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/twitter/RennesTwitter.phps</source_url>
            </file>
            <file>
                <name>markerTweet.php</name>
                <purpose>get tweets and sentiment for markers</purpose>
                <source_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/twitter/markerTweet.phps</source_url>
            </file>
            <file>
                <name>SentimentAnalysis.php</name>
                <purpose>sentiment analysis</purpose>
                <source_url>http://isa.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~ta2-meier/dsa/assignment/twitter/SentimentAnalysis.phps</source_url>
            </file>
                        
        </source_files>
    </component>
    <individual_comment>Implementing the comments feed using the twitter API was an interesting excercise in 
        API usage, aswell as an opportunity to practice php, mysql, javascripting, css, and html. Working with
        the twitter API initially presented a challange as Twitters 2.0 API uses a more complex authentication
        procedure (perhaps in an attempt to better control what has become a politically influential eco system).
        By using open sourced tools, however, I was able to overcome this challenge, and successfully create a twitter
        feed that follows the geocoded activity of each of the cities. Performing Sentiment anaylis was particularly 
        interesting, and although the technique that I used was primitive compared to more advance machine learning
        approaches, it introduced me to techniques used to analyse data from APIs. Futher work could
        expand on these concepts, and clearly valuable lessons to be learned from the 
        analysis of free data.
    </individual_comment>
   
</individual_metafile>
